<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>Void news</title>
	<subtitle>Follow Void Linux news</subtitle>
	<link href="https://voidlinux.org/"/>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://voidlinux.org/atom.xml"/>
	<updated>2022-06-02T19:33:09+00:00</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Void Linux Team</name>
	</author>
	<id>https://voidlinux.org/</id>


	<entry>
		<title>New Mirror Default</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/05/default-mirror.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/05/default-mirror</id>
		<published>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The default mirror has been updated to
https://repo-default.voidlinux.org.  If you wish to specify a mirror
that is nearer to you geographically you can find the full list of
currently active mirrors here:
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>US Mirror Retirement</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/10/mirror-retirement.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/10/mirror-retirement</id>
		<published>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The alpha.us.repo.voidlinux.org mirror has been retired.  Users should
switch to https://repo-us.voidlinux.org for continued service out of
the central US.  As part of the switch the US tier one mirror has
gained TLS, and is running on a more reliable host.</p>

<p>All contributors with in-flight PRs should rebase to ensure that the
latest URL is reflected in your branch’s CI configuration.</p>

</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Hacktoberfest 2021</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/hacktoberfest.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/hacktoberfest</id>
		<published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Are you ready for Hacktoberfest 2021?  Void Linux is!  We’re excited
to be participating for our 5th year.  Contributions that help to
address our out-of-date packages queue are especially welcome.  This
is a great way to dip your feet into the world of Linux distro package
management and what happens behind the scenes to provide a wide
selection of packages and make sure your system remains up to date.</p>

<p>Updating packages is very easy.  You can select a package from the
list of <a href="http://repo-default.voidlinux.org/void-updates/void-updates.txt">out of date
packages</a>
and update it using the tools in the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages">void-packages
repo</a>.  The
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md">manual</a>
might be of assistance when you are updating packages.</p>

<p>As a general rule, we recommend that newcommers to the Void Linux
project steer clear of “structural” packages unless you have specific
domain knowledge that qualifies you to work on high-risk packages.
When selecting a package to update, prefer packages registered to
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">orphan@voidlinux.org</code>.  These packages are otherwise unmaintained,
and your contribution will have a bigger impact.  You can update
packages that have a maintainer assigned, but understand that
conflicting changes between a maintainer and contributor will be
resolved at the discretion of Void staff.</p>

<p>Here are some useful tips when updating packages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>While we’re not completely opposed to PRs that add new packages,
you’re much more likely to get your PR approved and merged if it’s
a well written update.</li>
  <li>Don’t PR broken code. Our maintainers are much less likely to give
a second look to a PR that didn’t build when it was submitted.</li>
  <li>While it’s possible to run xbps-src from an alien distro, this
isn’t really supported.  If you’re a seasoned Linux user and want
to try Void, now is the time!</li>
  <li>The update list is sometimes wrong. We’d love to get patches that
improve its reliability by <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md#checking-for-new-upstream-releases">ignoring beta
versions</a>
or adding checks to packages that are not correctly detected as
out of date.</li>
  <li>If you have expertise in C, GNU Autotools, or other build systems,
taking a look at projects that we’ve marked as incompatible
with cross compilation and fixing the upstream issue can be
an amazing contribution that impacts more than just Void.</li>
</ul>

<p>We look forward to working with the amazing world of open source
developers this month to improve Void and continue our high standards
for quality and reliability.  To ensure your PR has the best chance at
being accepted, feel free to reach out for help as explained in the
manual.  Together, we can make this a high-impact Hacktoberfest.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>DigitalOcean Renews Sponsorship</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/sponsor-do-renew.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/sponsor-do-renew</id>
		<published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Void is pleased to announce that DigitalOcean has renewed their
sponsorship of our project as part of the <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/open-source/">Digital Ocean Open Source
program</a>.  DigitalOcean
provides us with reliable infrastructure on which we run the control
plane for our distributed fleet of machines, as well as some assorted
monitoring and fleet management services.  You can find our full list
of sponsors on the <a href="/acknowledgments/">Acknowledgements page</a>.</p>

<p>Should you also want to run a Void Linux VM on DigitalOcean’s droplet
service, we provide tooling for generating Void Linux images in <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-mklive">the
mklive repository</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Repository Signing Disruption</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/07/signing-disruption.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/07/signing-disruption</id>
		<published>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We are aware of an ongoing infrastructure issue affecting repository
synchronization and package signing.  We are working to resolve this
disruption, but first must resolve another unrelated infrastructure
issue.  We have no short term ETA for service restoration, however our
worst case resolution timeline is Friday the 23rd of July.</p>

<p>Your patience is appreciated while we perform this work as fast as
possible.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Void Linux freenode Channels Have Been Hijacked</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/freenode-takeover.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/freenode-takeover</id>
		<published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We have been made aware that during the mass channel takeover that is
ongoing on freenode that bogus <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">##voidlinux</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">##xbps</code> channels
have been created in the secondary namespace.</p>

<p>We do not operate or engage with these channels, and we do not
maintain an official presence on the freenode network.  We are still
in the process of finalizing the shutdown of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#xbps</code> and
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channels in the primary namespace, and have removed our
channels from the public listing as part of this process.</p>

<p>Though you should always exercise caution when running code obtained
from the internet, we urge you exercise extreme caution when using any
code from any channels on the freenode network that claims affiliation
with the Void Linux project.  You can always find our official points
of presence listed at the top of our <a href="/">home page</a>.</p>

<p>If you want to ask the Void team questions in real-time about this or
any other Void related matter, feel free to ask at any time in
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irc.libera.chat</code>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>IRC network switch to Libera</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/libera.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/libera</id>
		<published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Given the recent <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/856543/">upheaval at Freenode</a>, the
Void Linux team has made the decision to switch to another IRC network. Our
network of choice is <a href="https://libera.chat">libera.chat</a>, managed by former
Freenode staff. When accessing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#xbps</code>, be sure to use
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irc.libera.chat</code>! We are excited to welcome you there, and hope this doesn’t
inconvenience anyone unduly. Be sure to let us know of any issues.</p>

<p>Contacting us will remain the same: you can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://libera.chat">libera.chat</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>In memoriam pullmoll</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/In-memoriam-pullmoll.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/In-memoriam-pullmoll</id>
		<published>2021-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><center>
	<img src="/assets/img/pullmoll.png" alt="Picture of Pullmoll" />
</center>

<p>Today, we were informed that our long time contributor and maintainer Jürgen
Buchmüller (pullmoll) has passed away.</p>

<p>With boundless dedication, Jürgen was one of the most prolific contributors to
the Void project and sponsored the project financially, too.</p>

<p>He invested lots of his time in keeping GCC up to date and well tested, supplied tons of
patches to port packages to new compilers and platforms and also took care of
(co-)maintaining many packages, including several non-trivial ones, like OpenJDK
and LibreOffice.</p>

<p>He was not only a dedicated and driven developer in the Void Linux project, he
also was one of the friendliest and warmest people we had the pleasure to work
with. Jürgen will be missed as a steady force and a calm and wise voice in
discussions. Most of all, he will be remembered as a friend to all of us.</p>

<p>Our thoughts and condolences go out to Jürgen’s family, friends, and loved ones.</p>

<p><strong>Thank you, pullmoll.</strong></p>

<p>– The Void Linux maintainers</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Friday in the Void: OpenSSL and Kernel Hardening</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/OpenSSL-hardening-updates.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/OpenSSL-hardening-updates</id>
		<published>2021-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The previously announced <a href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL.html">OpenSSL switch</a>
is now underway. Because OpenSSL is a dependency of a large number of packages,
the full rebuild process is expected to take several days. Syncing between the
builders and public repositories has been suspended to ensure that the package
tree remains consistent. Consequently, no new package updates will appear until
the switch is complete.</p>

<p>Once updates appear, we recommend that you perform a complete system update to
simplify the transition. Partial updates are possible, but you will need to
manually trace all OpenSSL dependants installed on your system and update them
atomically.</p>

<hr />

<p>Since 2016, the default bootloader configuration in Void Linux has set
the Linux kernel command-line options <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">slub_debug=P</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">page_poison=1</code> to
provide some level of kernel hardening. Kernel series 5.3 and later offer
alternative measures <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free</code> (see <a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/commit/6471384af">this kernel
commit</a>).</p>

<p>Void’s kernels come with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> option enabled by default where
available (<em>i.e.</em>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.4&gt;=5.4.102</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.10&gt;=5.10.20</code> and
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.11&gt;=5.11.3</code>). In most cases, you should not disable this option, as it
has a fairly minimal impact on performance (within 1%). The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free</code>
option is more expensive (around 5% on average) and needs to be enabled by hand
by passing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free=1</code> on the kernel command line. Similarly,
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> can be disabled if needed by passing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc=0</code>.</p>

<p>As a consequence of these changes, Void’s default kernel command-line now omits
the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">slub_debug</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">page_poison</code> options. There is a chance that your
existing system still has the old options enabled. They still work in newer
kernels, but have a performance impact more in line with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free=1</code>. On
older hardware this can be quite noticeable. If you are running a kernel series
older than 5.4, you can keep them (or add them) for extra security at the cost
of performance; otherwise, you should remove them.</p>

<hr />

<p>As always, if you experience any issues, feel free to reach out to us! You can
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an issue</a> on
GitHub or seek help in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Switching back to OpenSSL</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL</id>
		<published>2021-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The Void Linux team is <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/21056">switching back to
OpenSSL</a> on March 5th,
2021 (2021-03-05).</p>

<p>For most users, there should be no noticeable change. If you have any packages
installed that are no longer provided by Void, or your system has explicit
dependencies on LibreSSL, you will of course need to take action to ensure your
system continues to function after the switch.</p>

<p>If you experience any issues, feel free to reach out to us! You can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>A discussion about switching to OpenSSL began in a Request For Comments (RFC)
posted on April 12th, 2020, at
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/20935">void-linux/void-packages#20935</a>.
Since then, a majority of Void maintainers have expressed support for the move.
The main reasons for the switch are as listed in the RFC:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Because most software targets OpenSSL, Void will no longer have to maintain
(in some cases, very complex) patches to support LibreSSL. The complexity of
the OpenSSL API makes such patching burdensome and risky, with mistakes
potentially causing runtime errors or security issues - we have avoided
those, as far as we know, but this has required a lot of effort.</li>
  <li>Extensive support for platform specific optimizations outside of x86.</li>
  <li>Access to new standards and algorithms earlier, such as full TLS 1.3 support.</li>
</ul>

<p>As a result of the above, the switch to OpenSSL is expected to lessen the time
and effort spent on packages that require an OpenSSL-like library. This is
especially notable because most other distributions which used LibreSSL have
dropped it, so there aren’t as many people amongst whom to distribute the
effort.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Alpine, which switched to LibreSSL temporarily, switched back to OpenSSL in
January 2019, with the <a href="https://alpinelinux.org/posts/Alpine-3.9.0-released.html">3.9.0
release</a>.</li>
  <li>More recently, Gentoo, which used to offer LibreSSL as an option, has
<a href="https://www.gentoo.org/support/news-items/2021-01-05-libressl-support-discontinued.html">discontinued that
support</a>
as well.</li>
</ul>

<p>For further context, LWN <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/841664/">covered the subject of LibreSSL on
Linux</a> at the beginning of this year. The
article also covers the attention and improvements that the OpenSSL project has
received post-Heartbleed, which was one of the main reasons for Void’s initial
switch to LibreSSL.</p>

<p>For an example of extra work caused by packages that expect OpenSSL, Void’s
version of Qt5 is heavily patched in order to properly support LibreSSL.
Furthermore, the just released Qt6 would also need significant effort to be
patched and maintained to use LibreSSL, without the possibility of such effort
being upstreamed.</p>

<p>At the same time, other software can have limited functionality or hit edge
cases when using LibreSSL, due to not being thoroughly tested with it. One
example is Python, which is limited in the ciphers available to running
programs, since it depends on what the SSL library provides - they are even
<a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0644/#libressl-support">considering dropping any support for LibreSSL in the
future</a>. Another
example is OpenVPN, which we have received bug reports for connection issues
with LibreSSL
(<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/23413">void-linux/void-packages#23413</a>).
This required us to switch the package to use Mbed TLS by default, resulting in
some limitations to the resulting package. With the switch to OpenSSL, the
OpenVPN package will now be provided in the most widely deployed and tested
configuration, so similar compatibility hiccups are unlikely to reappear.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this move has required us to drop some packages that rely on the
OpenSSL 1.0.1 API; while LibreSSL maintains compatibility with this legacy API,
modern OpenSSL has abandoned it.</p>

<p>One great feature of LibreSSL not offered by OpenSSL is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libtls</code> library,
which aims to be a hard to misuse interface for communicating over the web
safely, with sane defaults. Some of the packages we ship depend on it, so work
has been done to package a standalone version of it in
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/28732">void-linux/void-packages#28732</a>.</p>

<p>The Void Linux team is grateful for the work of the OpenBSD community on
<a href="https://github.com/libressl-portable/portable">libressl-portable</a>, we have
greatly benefited from their work. Void continues to package other excellent
OpenBSD software, including OpenSSH and signify, which is our tool of choice
for signing live images.</p>

<p>In conclusion, we expect our switch to OpenSSL to ease maintenance overhead,
provide the same reliable experience to users, and improve functionality in
select packages. Look forward to the update landing some time after March 5th!</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New Images!</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/new-images.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/new-images</id>
		<published>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We’re pleased to announce that the 20210218 image set has been
promoted to current and is now generally available.</p>

<p>You can find the new images on our <a href="/download/">downloads page</a> and on
our many <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">mirrors</a>.</p>

<p>Special thanks for this image set goes out to @ericonr for work in
validating the images, and to @paper42 for providing us a new image in
the grub splash screen.</p>

<p>You may verify the authenticity of the images by following the
instructions on the downloads page, and using the following signify
key information:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>untrusted comment: This key is only valid for images with date 20210218. public key
RWRSNnH5WbLx1EWUgJGeccx/Dof1MH5k5tZFytMlIOgpRJvRxHJtMqrP
</code></pre></div></div>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Upcoming glibc upgrade requires updates for other packages on 32-bit machines</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/01/glibc-2.32.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/01/glibc-2.32</id>
		<published>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p><strong>Note:</strong> This only applies to users of Void’s glibc version on 32-bit
machines. If the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps-uhelper arch</code> prints something other than
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i686</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv7l</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv6l</code>, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv6l-musl</code>, you don’t need to do
anything.</p>

<p>Void Linux currently packages glibc version 2.30, but is going to update to
2.32 soon, together with the long awaited GCC 10. Since this new version makes
use of new system calls, due to the ongoing time64 (support for times after
2038 on 32-bit platforms) work on glibc, applications with restrictive seccomp
filters that haven’t been rebuilt for the new glibc version <strong>will stop
working</strong>. Packages with such issues include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">firefox</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chromium</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qt5-webengine</code> (and consequently dependants, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qutebrowser</code>)</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">electron*</code> (and consequently dependants, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">element-desktop</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>We will be pushing updates to these packages <em>before</em> the glibc update, if
possible, but it won’t be possible for all of them. This includes <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code>,
which means you can be <strong>locked out of your system</strong> if that’s what you use to
access it and you perform a partial upgrade that only includes the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code>
package.</p>

<p>Therefore, even though Void enables partial upgrades, you should perform a full
system upgrade when <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code> appears in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps-install -Su</code> list. Be sure to
test these packages - for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code> this includes actually opening a session,
since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sshd</code> itself runs without issue. If for some reason something in your
system stops working, you can of course reinstall the old <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code> package using
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xtools.1">xdowngrade(1)</a> from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xtools</code> package:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code># xdowngrade /var/cache/xbps/glibc-2.30_2.x86_64.xbps /var/cache/xbps/glibc-locales-2.30_2.x86_64.xbps
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If we missed some package with this issue, please let us know! You can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Upcoming PAM upgrade requires review of custom configurations</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/12/pam-1.5.1.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/12/pam-1.5.1</id>
		<published>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Void Linux currently packages PAM version 1.3.0 and, until today, a standard
PAM configuration that requires the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_tally</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_lastlog</code>
authentication modules. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_tally</code> module was
<a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/linux-pam/linux-pam/master/NEWS">deprecated in 1.4.0 and removed in 1.5.0</a>,
and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_lastlog</code> module is no longer built for musl systems. The Void team
plans to <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/25506">upgrade to PAM 1.5.1</a>
by the end of the year.</p>

<p>For the upgraded PAM to function properly, any <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_tally</code> (and, for musl
users, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_lastlog</code>) requirements must be removed from the configuration files
in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/pam.d</code>. An updated <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/commit/e065ac229d78c4a1819098c7bda45bbd717120ba"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam-base</code> package</a>
released today removes the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_tally</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_lastlog</code> requirements from the
standard configuration. If you have not modified the standard PAM
configuration and have not enabled the XBPS <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">keepconf</code> option described in
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps.d.5"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps.d(5)</code></a>, upgrading the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam-base</code>
package should be sufficient to adjust your configuration.</p>

<p>Whether or not you have modified the PAM configuration, please make sure to
upgrade <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam-base</code> and confirm that no configuration files in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/pam.d</code>
contain references to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_tally</code> module (and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pam_lastlog</code> on musl)
<strong>before</strong> upgrading to PAM 1.5.1 when it becomes available.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Passwords generated with previous versions of rclone might be unsafe</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/11/rclone-1.53.3.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/11/rclone-1.53.3</id>
		<published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/commit/c2f27e9a75169e6bdc67f420d5e8a12648a8d8f0">latest rclone update</a>
to version 1.53.3 fixes
<a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2020-28924">CVE-2020-28924</a>.
From the <a href="https://forum.rclone.org/t/rclone-1-53-3-release/20569">release announcement</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some passwords generated with rclone config may be insecure. In
particular if you used the ‘g’ generate option with rclone
v1.49 - v1.53.2 then your password will based on the second it was
generated in. This means that there are fixed number of passwords
in that period ~33 million.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We updated the rclone package to version 1.49.0, the first one affected,
on August 27, 2019. The upstream project recommends using their
<a href="https://github.com/rclone/passwordcheck">passwordcheck</a> utility to verify
that your passwords aren’t among the ~33 million vulnerable ones. On a
Void Linux system, you can obtain this utility by installing the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">go</code>
package and then building <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">passwordcheck</code> locally:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code># xbps-install -S go
$ go get github.com/rclone/passwordcheck
</code></pre></div></div>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Hacktoberfest and Void Linux</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/10/hacktoberfest.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/10/hacktoberfest</id>
		<published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p><em>Update:</em> Unfortunately due to recent changes that significantly
increase the effort required from Void, we can no longer promise that
your changes will count towards the 4 PRs required for Hacktoberfest.</p>

<p>Many maintainers use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git am</code> in a script to apply patches and batch
them into build units that the buildbot can work on at a time.  This
precludes the application of labels unless the maintainer separately
opens a browser, logs into GitHub, and interacts with the PR there.
While the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git am</code> method should technically work, we’ve noticed in
the past that GitHub occasionally applies the wrong status to PRs
using this method (ignores magic closing words).  We aren’t currently
aware why this works intermittently and we can’t guarantee that a
specific PR will satisfy the new requirements for Hacktoberfest.</p>

<p>It’s unfortunate that the rules were changed mid-run, as under the
previous rules we could process contributions without disruptive
alterations to our review process, and we could accept many first time
contributors’ work to low-risk packages.  You are of course still
welcome to send your patches and they will be reviewed at the
avaiability of the Void team.</p>

<hr />

<p>It’s the first day of October, the air is crisp in parts of the
northern hemisphere, and it’s time for
<a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/">Hacktoberfest</a> again.  This
year is shaping up to be bigger than previous years, and as Void has
participated since the start we’d like to provide some helpful tips
and tricks for sending your first Pull Requests (PRs) to Void.</p>

<p>This year Void is accepting patches for two main areas, patches from
unknown contributors beyond these areas have a high likelihood of
being dismissed, so please color within the lines.</p>

<p>The first area is for non-code contributions.  We maintain all of our
documentation using a tool called
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/mdBook">mdBook</a>.  This has the net
effect that all of our documentation is written as version controlled
markdown files.  If you regularly use Void and have been looking for a
place to get involved, this is a good point to jump in.  We aren’t
trying to recreate the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/">ArchWiki</a> though,
so make sure you understand the scope and purpose of the docs repo
before sending your documentation.</p>

<p>For technical contributions, we are accepting updates of existing
packages.  While new packages may count as well, we have had many
problems in the past with people adding packages and then abandoning
them, so expect to meet significant resistance if you are a new
contributor trying to add a package to the repo.  Updating packages is
very easy.  You can select a package from the list of <a href="http://repo-default.voidlinux.org/void-updates/void-updates.txt">out of date
packages</a>
and update it using the tools in the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages">void-packages
repo</a>.  The
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md">manual</a>
might be of assistance when you are updating packages.</p>

<p>As a general rule, we would prefer Hacktoberfest contributors that do
not have a previous track record with the Void Linux project steer
clear of “structural” packages unless you have specific domain
knowledge that qualifies you to work on high-risk packages.  When
selecting a package to update, select a package registered to
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">orphan@voidlinux.org</code> when possible.  These packages are otherwise
unmaintained, and your contribution will have a bigger impact.  You
can update packages that are owned by existing developers, but
understand that conflicts between a maintainer and contributor will be
resolved at the discretion of Void staff.</p>

<p>Here are some useful tips when updating packages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Don’t PR broken code, our maintainers are much less likely to give
a second look to a PR that didn’t build when it was submitted.</li>
  <li>While it’s possible to run xbps-src from an alien distro, this
isn’t really supported.  If you’re a seasonsed Linux user and want
to try Void, now is the time!</li>
  <li>The docs use <a href="https://github.com/bobertlo/vmd">versioned
markdown</a>, available in the
vmdfmt package.  You can run this locally to format your files.</li>
  <li>The update list is sometimes wrong, we’d love to get patches that
improve its reliability by ignoring beta versions or adding checks
to packages that are not detected as out of date correctly.</li>
  <li>If you have expertise in C, GNU Autotools, or other build systems,
taking a look at projects that we’ve marked as not
cross-compilation compatible and fixing the upstream issue can be
an amazing contribution that impacts more than just Void.</li>
</ul>

<p>We look forward to working with the amazing world of open source
developers this month to improve Void and continue our high standards
for quality and reliability.  To ensure your PR has the best chance at
being accepted, feel free to reach out for help as explained in the
manual.  Together this will be a high impact Hacktoberfest.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Welcome New Contributors!</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/05/new-contributors.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/05/new-contributors</id>
		<published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The Void project is pleased to welcome onboard 3 new members today.</p>

<p>Joining us to work on packages is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@abenson</code>.</p>

<p>Joining us to advance the docs site are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@flexibeast</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@ericonr</code>.</p>

<p>Interested in seeing your name in a future update here?  Read our
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/contributing/index.html">Contributing Page</a>
and join us today!</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Some Context for Recent Events</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/04/some-context.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/04/some-context</id>
		<published>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><h3 id="notice">Notice</h3>

<p>This article is being actively edited and amended for both grammar and
to answer new questions as they come up.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>12:05 PST - Feedback from IRC for English, clarification of the
timeline of xtraeme’s resignation and subsequent ban.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>12:17 PST - Correct innaccuracies in the musl section.  My
understanding of the bug was incorrect (@the-maldridge).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2020-04-27 - Correct xtraeme’s pronouns, spelling/grammar cleanup</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>First a disclaimer.  This is written from my point of view
(@the-maldridge), and while it may contain views and opinions of the
project, you should assume these are my views.  This is posted here
and in the official name-space of Void Linux as questions have asked
that demand answers.  I hope that in this post I can provide some
answers.</p>

<p>To answer the immediate question of the day, Juan RP (xtraeme) has
chosen to leave the Void Linux project.</p>

<p>There will be no noticeable disruption to users, and the project will
continue as before.  We appreciate your support of Void and continuing
to advance the state of the void.  To any maintainer or contributor
that was on the receiving end of one of xtraeme’s recent posts, I
would like to extend the my apologies for this and those of the
project.  Void is a project we intend all to be involved in, and that
means treating others with respect.</p>

<p>I’d now like to answer a few questions that came to my mind as this
situation developed.  I’m on the West coast of the US, so I woke up to
a lot of this already in progress, but I also have a lot more
historical context than what is easily find-able.  Keep in mind that
out of respect for Juan’s privacy, I am deliberately not revealing
some information they chose to reveal to project maintainers.  They
may have left a sour taste with me, but they still have a right to
privacy like anyone else, and if they wish to share details of their
personal life, that is their decision and theirs alone.</p>

<h2 id="how-will-the-project-survive-without-xtraeme">How will the project survive without xtraeme?</h2>

<p>Short: Like we have before.</p>

<p>Long: This is not the first time xtraeme has left Void.  I wrote about
this on my personal site back in 2018, and you can read that full
<a href="https://michaelwashere.net/post/2018-11-28-enobdfl/">article</a> over
there.  Running a project like Void means ensuring that there is no
single point of failure.  We have a healthy pool of developers, and
short of perhaps some folks wanting to take some time off to recover
from the events of the day, I fully expect the project will continue
as it has.</p>

<h2 id="the-thread-on-github-mentioned-xtraeme-has-broken-things-in-the-past">The thread on GitHub mentioned xtraeme has broken things in the past?</h2>

<p>Being rolling release and not breaking things involves a lot of
coordination.  Some of this coordination is baked into the software.
For example, you can’t update your system while large rebuilds are in
progress because that would install incompatible versions of some
libraries (we’re working on improving the user experience around this
though).</p>

<p>Some of the recent changes that come to mind in no particular order:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Pushing a musl update with no coordination.  For context around
the change, see <a href="http://musl.libc.org/time64.html">this link</a>.</p>

    <p>This is something we’re planning a lot of work around because
updating the C library will involve recompiling almost everything
on musl against it.  Normally there’s ABI compatibility, but for
reasons far beyond the scope of this article, musl is different.
There is an ongoing dialog in #musl on freenode with some Alpine
devs as well trying to determine the best way to do this upgrade.</p>

    <p>Updated: The original version referenced 1.2 of musl.  This was
incorrect as the interactions that caused this problem are not
unique to this version.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pushing a glibc update with no coordination.  We saw the trouble
that befell Arch when they did a glibc update that temporarily
broke bash.  We’d hoped to avoid this same fate, but while
discussing the change, the package was merged without discussion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>General problems related to single points of failure.  Though
this is not an issue now, there was a time where xtraeme was the
single point of failure.  Through their personal inaction we lost
the voidlinux.eu domain.  We had a lot of trouble getting the
project back into a stable state, but through a significant amount
of effort, we recovered.  Though newer maintainers probably don’t
notice this, there are a lot of older developers and users who
remember when xtraeme was all that Void was.  The project has
grown significantly since then, and this is a change I’m not sure
xtraeme ever fully adjusted to.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="i-feel-like-youre-not-telling-a-lot-of-stuff-where-can-i-get-that-context">I feel like you’re not telling a lot of stuff, where can I get that context?</h2>

<p>For better or for worse, a lot of discussions happen behind closed
doors.  We don’t feel it is our place as Void Linux to air the dirty
laundry of maintainers and contributors.  What goes on in your
personal life outside of Void is not our concern, and we have no right
to tell others your secrets.  That being said, all factors are
considered when evaluating granting or removing a commit bit.  Note
that according to <a href="https://infradocs.voidlinux.org">InfraDocs</a> almost
all of the initial discussion of onboarding and offboarding
maintainers happens on private forums.  These discussions are pretty
mundane, usually along the lines of “have they broken anything?” or
“wow, this person does a lot of work really fast”.  The discussions
around xtraeme unfortunately have been of the form “their conduct
towards others really isn’t great, but I’m not comfortable approaching
them.”</p>

<h2 id="does-void-profit-from-xtraemes-work">Does Void profit from xtraeme’s work?</h2>

<p>While Void and its users <em>benefit</em> from the work of all developers,
including xtraeme, no profit is derived from this work.</p>

<p>Void is an Open Source project, it always has been and will continue
to be one.  You are free to use the code within the confines of the
license.  Since Void is permissively licensed, you are welcome to use
it commercially as well, though please be a good citizen of the FOSS
community and upstream your patches when practical.</p>

<p>Should xtraeme wish to change the license of their copy of XBPS, we
will evaluate the situation.</p>

<p>Void does not accept donations.  We appreciate the efforts of those
that reach out from time to time wishing to support the project
financially, but our expenses are minimal.  If you want to contribute,
you can help by updating packages, reviewing issues, or generally
being a part of the community.  If an individual maintainer chooses to
solicit or accept a donation for their work, this is done separately
from the project.  International tax law is a complicated beast, and
as a project we’re not comfortable accepting donations until we have
the infrastructure in place to show where the money goes, and provide
you with appropriate documentation.</p>

<h2 id="did-xtraeme-resign-or-were-they-banned">Did xtraeme resign, or were they banned?</h2>

<p>Timing is everything.  The ticket which expressed xtraeme’s desire to
resign was opened first, then over the next hour they lashed out at
several project members.  The resignation was processed per their
wishes, and per their conduct torwards others, a ban was applied at
the organization level.</p>

<h2 id="i-want-to-talk-to-someone-about-this">I want to talk to someone about this.</h2>

<p>Sure, we live in interesting times, and talking to others is a great
way to cope with unexpected change.  Feel free to chat on Void’s
official IRC channel <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> on freenode.  You can also find us
at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">r/voidlinux</code> on Reddit.  We also maintain a mailing list which you
can find on the website.</p>

<h1 id="what-happens-now">What happens now?</h1>

<p>Remember these are my words (@the-maldridge) not necessarily those of
the project.</p>

<p>This is a really uncomfortable place to be in.  None of us want to
start a Twitter war, and at the end of the day, Void is about working
on software we all believe in.</p>

<p>Void will continue.  We do appreciate the work that xtraeme did to get
us here, projects like Void need someone to have an idea and run with
it, then convince others to join you.  xtraeme was that early person
with an idea, there’s no denying this.  It’s sad that this
collaboration had to end this way.  I would be lying if I said this
was a surprise to me, but I truly did not in my wildest imagination
expect it to play out like this.</p>

<h3 id="enough-of-politics-diplomacy-and-speaking-as-a-project-what-do-you-think-about-all-this">Enough of Politics, Diplomacy, and speaking as a project, what do YOU think about all this?</h3>

<p>The last 8 months since xtraeme showed up again have been a roller
coaster.  It’s been a stressful time and I’ve come very close to
leaving the project several times.  I’m one of a handful of people who
directly maintain the day to day infrastructure that builds and serves
Void, and that made me the receiving end of more than one rant.  I’m
going to take a step back and think about if I want to continue this
project or work on one of my own more.  When I started working on Void
I was in college and employed by a university that was running Void
internally (sadly, they no longer do).  I had a lot more free time
then, and Void was a lot less stressful to work on.</p>

<p>xtraeme is a talented C developer; there is no denying this, and I
respect their work on XBPS.  It is certainly not without bugs, but
no one’s code is.  I am personally upset that this is how this had to
end.  I expected at some point xtraeme would part ways with the
project, as their goals and those of the project have diverged.  I am
upset that they felt the need to take out their frustration on
contributors and maintainers, and that is why the decision was made to
ban them from the organization.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>OpenSSH 8.2 update requires restart of sshd</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/02/openssh-8.2.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/02/openssh-8.2</id>
		<published>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>With the OpenSSH update to 8.2 you <em>must</em> restart the
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sshd</code> service, or it will not accept new ssh connections.</p>

<p>XBPS will print a notice about this when updating OpenSSH,
but we hope by posting this notice we will reach the
users who don’t read the output of regular updates
and avoid or minimize complications due to the update.</p>

<p>We considered restarting sshd automatically on update,
but the policy of not restarting, enabling or otherwise
interact with services during updates stands.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>News about XBPS</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/01/xbps-news.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/01/xbps-news</id>
		<published>2020-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>XBPS 0.58 was just released, with many new features and a lot of improvements.
Since the last post was for 0.54, this post includes all changes and some highlights since the last post.</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<h3 id="performance-improvements">Performance improvements</h3>

<p>Some users might have noticed that removing the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plasma-desktop</code> was very time consuming because of dependency cycles.
The dependency resolution algorithm has been completely rewritten and is now able to resolve the dependencies of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plasma-desktop</code> within seconds.</p>

<p>See the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/xbps/pull/78">pull request void-linux/xbps#78</a> if you are interested in what changed.</p>

<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--fulldeptree</code> flag of <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-query.1">xbps-query(1)</a> in combination with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-x</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-X</code> for dependencies and reverse dependencies respectively has been improved and will now be 50x faster in the worst case scenario.</p>

<h3 id="ignorepkg-configuration-option"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ignorepkg</code> configuration option</h3>

<p>Many users tried to get rid of the default kernel or some other <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">base-system</code> requirement.
For this we’ve added a new configuration keyword: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ignorepkg</code>.</p>

<p>With this new keyword you can ignore packages that are pulled in by other packages as runtime dependencies.</p>

<p>As example you can add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux-firmware-amd</code> as ignored package and then uninstall the package:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code># echo "ignorepkg=linux-firmware-amd" &gt; /etc/xbps.d/10-ignore.conf
# xbps-remove linux-firmware-amd
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This works for any package, i.e. being able to remove <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux4.19</code> while keeping the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux</code> meta package.
Or removing the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux</code> meta package itself and installing only the kernel series you like to use yourself.</p>

<h3 id="noextract-configuration-option"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">noextract</code> configuration option</h3>

<p>Another useful new feature is the new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">noextract</code>, it allows to specify patterns of
files that should not be extracted when installing or updating packages.</p>

<p>This allows as example to skip extracting translations the users are not interesting in,
allowing to reduce the installation size.</p>

<p>We plan to make use of it in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps-src</code> to cut down the time required to install build dependencies.</p>

<h2 id="download-only-flag">Download only flag</h2>

<p>A new flag was added to <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a> which allows to
download packages and its dependencies without installing them.</p>

<h2 id="changelog">Changelog</h2>

<h3 id="xbps-058-2020-01-30">xbps-0.58 (2020-01-30):</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>libfetch: fix <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/security/advisories/FreeBSD-SA-20:01.libfetch.asc">CVE-2020-7450</a>; from FreeBSD. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-query.1">xbps-query(1)</a>, <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-remove.1">xbps-remove(1)</a>: improved detection
of orphans, needing multiple iterations to collect
all of them in a single transaction. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-checkvers.1">xbps-checkvers(1)</a>: added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-e, --removed</code>.
To list removed templates in srcpkgs. <a href="https://github.com/Chocimier">[Chocimier]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: improved <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-D, --download-only</code>.
This now can be used to download all required
binary packages of the target pkg without the need
to have write permission to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rootdir</code>.</p>

    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ xbps-install -c $PWD/cachedir -Dy xbps
</code></pre></div>    </div>

    <p>NOTE: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-c, --cachedir</code> must be specified as absolute
pathname, otherwise it will treat it as relative to
rootdir. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-fetch.1">xbps-fetch(1)</a>: added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-s</code> to print sha256sums of
downloaded files. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>configure: re-add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--enable-debug</code> and enable it
by default. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: ignore indirect reverse dependencies
while updating xbps. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--reproducible</code> long option.
If set, enables reproducible mode in pkgdb. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: don’t prompt if all packages in
the transaction are on hold. [Mohamad Barbar]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-rindex.1">xbps-rindex(1)</a>: stop adding the “build-date” pkg obj.
Contained wrong info and did not provide enough value
to be useful; another step towards reproducibility.
<a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-create.1">xbps-create(1)</a>: always sanitize gathered symlinks. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: do not silently update <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps</code> on
any install/update transaction. If there’s a new update
for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps</code> package, this needs to be explicitely
declared as a single transaction, i.e:</p>

    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> $ xbps-install -u xbps
</code></pre></div>    </div>

    <p>Otherwise it will return <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">EBUSY</code> (16), making this a proper
error code to diagnose what failed. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps.d.5">xbps.d(5)</a>: new ‘noextract’ configuration option,
to skip extracting files matching a pattern. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps.d.5">xbps.d(5)</a>: autodetected ‘architecture’ (glibc or musl)
at compile-time on linux systems. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>configure: added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--enable-lto</code> and don’t enable it
by default. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Multiple bugs with packages on hold were fixed. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-uchroot.1">xbps-uchroot(1)</a>, <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-uunshare.1">xbps-uunshare(1)</a>: document end of
options argument. <a href="https://github.com/sgn">[Doan Tran Cong Danh]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-alternatives.1">xbps-alternatives(1)</a>: prune obsolete alternatives groups. <a href="https://github.com/q66">[q66]</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>17 new test cases were added in this release, 6 people
were involved: Juan RP, Piotr Wójcik, Duncan Overbruck,
Doan Tran Cong Danh, Mohamad Barbar, q66.</p>

<h3 id="xbps-0571-2019-10-27">xbps-0.57.1 (2019-10-27):</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Multiple changes and improvements to the transaction
fetch code. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Verify revision in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps_pkg_{version,revision,name}</code>,
to handle properly package names that use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_</code>.
<a href="https://github.com/Chocimier">[Chocimier]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-checkvers.1">xbps-checkvers(1)</a>: fixed a compile-time warning with glibc.
<a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-alternatives.1">xbps-alternatives(1)</a>: check if alternative is a
symlink before removing it. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Try to find a usable shell instead of using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/bin/sh</code>
when executing package scripts. <a href="https://github.com/Gottox">[Gottox]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-rindex.1">xbps-rindex(1)</a>: better error handling for writing repodata
archives. <a href="https://github.com/Chocimier">[Chocimier]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-create.1">xbps-create(1)</a>: better error handling for writing archives.
<a href="https://github.com/Chocimier">[Chocimier]</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="xbps-057-2019-08-06">xbps-0.57 (2019-08-06):</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>xbps now builds with tcc and pcc. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>xbps now uses the transactional file checks for package removals,
this fixes issues where xbps removes wrong files, if a package
replaces another packages with the same files. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-remove.1">xbps-remove(1)</a>: skip the transaction if no packages are found.
This restores the behaviour of xbps prior to 0.54. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-remove.1">xbps-remove(1)</a>: fix <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-o, --remove-orphans</code> not removing
all orphaned packages. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: if specified packages with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-u, --update</code> are
up to date return EEXIST. <a href="https://github.com/jnbr">[jnbr]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-query.1">xbps-query(1)</a>: restores old behaviour of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--fulldeptree</code>,
to not list the package itself. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Updated zsh completions. <a href="https://github.com/leah2">[leah2]</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="xbps-056-2019-06-24">xbps-0.56 (2019-06-24):</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps_transaction_prepare()</code> always returning
ENXIO because the transaction dictionary wasn’t
initialized before first use. Regression from 0.54. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed unlocking the pkgdb via <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps_end()</code>. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed flushing pkgdb to storage and re-reading it unnecessarily,
this affected <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-alternatives.1">xbps-alternatives(1)</a>,
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-pkgdb.1">xbps-pkgdb(1)</a> and
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-reconfigure.1">xbps-reconfigure(1)</a>.
<a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>xbps now allows to remove an installed package that was
added to the ignored packages list with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ignorepkg</code> from
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps.d.5">xbps.d(5)</a>. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed an issue with multi threaded for each loops
processing the first slicecount*maxthreads entries twice. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed an issue with happy eyeballs, where when a socket
fails within the connection delay it aborts with the error
instead of continuing with the next address. <a href="https://github.com/jnbr">[jnbr]</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="xbps-055-2019-06-21">xbps-0.55 (2019-06-21):</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: Added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-D, --download-only</code> flag to allow
downloading packages to the cache without attempting to
install them. <a href="https://github.com/Vaelatern">[Vaelatern]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-I, --ignore-file-conflicts</code> to not abort
the transaction even if file conflicts were detected. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-install.1">xbps-install(1)</a>: return 0 if package is already installed,
or up-to-date if updating, not <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">EEXIST</code>. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">EEXIST</code> now is only
returned if there are file conflicts in transaction. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xbps-checkvers.1">xbps-checkvers(1)</a>: fixed a segfault with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--format</code>. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed a build failure on ppc64. <a href="https://github.com/q66">[q66]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed a build failure on x86. <a href="https://github.com/Duncaen">[duncaen]</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fixed cross compilation with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--enable-static</code>. <a href="https://github.com/xtraeme">[xtraeme]</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New images and new verification keys</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/01/new-images.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2020/01/new-images</id>
		<published>2020-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We’re pleased to announce that the 20191109 image set has been
promoted to current and is now generally available.</p>

<p>A change that comes along with these new images is the adoption of
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">signify(1)</code> to verify images.  We’re saying goodbye to PGP due to the
complexity involved, the relative difficulty in verifying the
resulting signature, and the questionable state of PGP key
distribution right now.</p>

<p>The downloads page has been updated with instructions for how you can
validate new images, and we hope you’ll find this process easier and
faster than in previous releases.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>


</feed>
