<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>Void news</title>
	<subtitle>Follow Void Linux news</subtitle>
	<link href="https://voidlinux.org/"/>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://voidlinux.org/atom.xml"/>
	<updated>2023-05-30T05:42:19+00:00</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Void Linux Team</name>
	</author>
	<id>https://voidlinux.org/</id>


	<entry>
		<title>Breaking changes: Pipewire session manager switch, Pipewire and PulseAudio system service removal</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/05/audio-breakage.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/05/audio-breakage</id>
		<published>2023-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><h3 id="pipewire-session-manager-switch">Pipewire session manager switch</h3>

<p>Void has now dropped the long-deprecated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire-media-session</code> session manager
from its <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code> package, bringing it inline with the upstream default
configuration. If you are currently using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code>, you must migrate to
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wireplumber</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code> will cease to function properly. Refer to
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/config/media/pipewire.html#session-management">Void documentation</a>
if you need guidance when making this change.</p>

<h3 id="pipewire-and-pulseaudio-system-service-removal">Pipewire and PulseAudio system service removal</h3>

<p>The oft-confusing services for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire-pulse</code>,
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wireplumber</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pulseaudio</code> have been removed from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code>,
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wireplumber</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pulseaudio</code> packages because they were experimental and
should not have been used for almost all use-cases.</p>

<p>If you are currently using those services and still wish to do so, replacements
for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pulseaudio</code> services can be found in
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/usr/share/examples/$pkgname/sv/</code>. Otherwise, it is recommended to migrate to
another method of launching <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pipewire</code>. Refer to
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/config/media/pipewire.html">Void documentation</a>
if you need guidance.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New Repo: Fastly CDN</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/1-new-repo-fastly.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/1-new-repo-fastly</id>
		<published>2023-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>In our last post we showed you how to quickly change your mirror using
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xmirror.1">xmirror</a>.  In this post we’ll
give you a reason to use it, and talk a little more about how mirrors
work and how packages get from our servers, to your computer.</p>

<p>Before we can mirror packages, we first need to build some.  Void uses
a worker-based build architecture where a central controller
dispatches build tasks to individual servers that own the builds for
specific architectures.  At the time of writing, Void makes use of
discrete builders for aarch64 targets, assorted musl targets, and
assorted glibc targets.  The breakdown is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a-fsn-de
    <ul>
      <li>x86_64</li>
      <li>i686</li>
      <li>armv6l</li>
      <li>armv7l</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>b-fsn-de
    <ul>
      <li>aarch64</li>
      <li>aarch64-musl</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>a-hel-fi
    <ul>
      <li>x86_64-musl</li>
      <li>armv6l-musl</li>
      <li>armv7l-musl</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Each build server drives, via automation, a standard git checkout of
the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages">void-packages repo</a>.
This in turn results in built binary packages ready for installation
in the path <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/hostdir/binpkgs</code> on each of the build machines.  To
actually be useful, however, the packages need to be aggregated and
then signed, then copied out to servers near to end users such that
packages are quick to download and install whenever required.</p>

<p>Packages are aggregated via nomad managed rsync tasks to a-fsn-de.
Since a-fsn-de already hosts several architectures, its packages don’t
need to be moved.  You might recognize the target directories from the
repo URL structure.  The packages originating on a-hel-fi are copied
to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/hostdir/binpkgs/musl</code> and the packages from b-fsn-de are copied
to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/hostdir/binpkgs/aarch64</code>.  Once the packages are all in one
place, they can be signed.  This is also handled by a nomad managed
batch task.</p>

<p>Once signed, a complete, ready to distribute package collection exists
on a-fsn-de, however this isn’t where any mirror synchronizes from,
nor is it where end users obtain packages from.  The first real
“mirror” in the chain with the full contents, including live images,
docs, and other mirror contents is on a-hel-fi and is sometimes
referred to by the Void team as the “Shadow Repo”.  When we make large
builds that we know in advance will cause issues for end users, we
disconnect all downstream repos from the shadow repo and this allows
us to run large builds without impacting user’s ability to install or
update already extant packages.</p>

<p>Tier 1 (Void Operated) mirrors synchronize directly from the Shadow
Repo, again via nomad managed batch tasks.  All downstream mirrors
synchronize from one or more tier 1 mirrors, with one notable
exception which we’ll come back to.  These mirrors are operated by
universities, companies, and individuals who desire to have a copy of
the Void repository closer to them.  This allows for faster installs,
faster updates, and in many cases more efficient bandwidth usage where
a mirror is able to be co-located with multiple Void users.</p>

<p>By and large, these mirrors synchronize using rsync on cron timers.
Some synchronize very frequently, as frequently as every 15 minutes.
Some synchronize more slowly, only once a day.  And some mirrors often
appear broken and don’t appear to have synced at all.  How can we
possibly know this?  Well we drop a file into the root of the mirror
at the Shadow level with a timestamp.  By watching the value in this
file, we can tell how old the contents of any downstream repo are.
All this information is exposed in our <a href="https://grafana.s.voidlinux.org/d/cLraC-XMk/mirrors-status">mirror
dashboard</a>.
The “Origin” referenced in that dashboard is a slight misnomer, its
actually showing the time behind <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">now</code>.</p>

<p>Having multiple mirrors is great, but ensuring that a mirror nearby to
a user who wants to update, and make sure they’ve configured and are
using it is a bit harder.  What we really want is a proxy that will
always find the nearest mirror and fetch packages from that location
for a user.  Long-time users of Void may remember <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">auto.voidlinux.org</code>
which was an early attempt at this.  Due to limitations in XBPS
itself, and limitations in the way that we are able to introspect
mirrors, this service was eventually retracted.  What we actually want
is a network of servers everywhere well connected to networks that
users are on, and then with a good connection back to at least one of
the Void operated mirrors.  This, as you might have guessed, is a CDN.</p>

<p>As mentioned in the <a href="/news/2023/01/fastly-fast-forward.html">Fast
Forward</a> post, Void has
generously been sponsored by Fastly, which has allowed us to provision
a new repository URL that leverage’s Fastly’s global network to
provide what should be the generally optimal mirror regardless of
where in the world any particular end user exists.  The Fastly mirror
does not sync, nor does it have a concept of file storage that we
manage as the project.  It is for all intents and purposes an
extremely large high-speed cache, and when you request a package from
Fastly, the package will either be returned from one of Fastly’s
servers, or it will be streamed to you via the Fastly network while
being simultaneously fetched from one of Void’s backend servers.  The
very first download of a package may be slower than if you downloaded
it from Void directly, but all subsequent fetches will be extremely
fast.  Since the package distribution follows a sort of curve of
popularity ranging from the common packages that make up desktop
environments, the base system, and popular software suites down to
less commonly installed packages and rarely updated libraries, the
cache will usually be hot for the most commonly installed packages!</p>

<p>So to recap, packages are built on servers, copied to a central
server, signed, copied to a shadow mirror, copied to a tier 1 mirror,
possibly copied to downstream mirrors, and then installed on end
systems.  Here’s a graphic:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/mirrors.svg" alt="diagram of the package flow" style="max-height: 80vh" /></p>

<p>We hope you’ve enjoyed this look into what it takes to get packages
from us to you, but more importantly, we’re pleased to announce now
the general availability of <a href="https://repo-fastly.voidlinux.org/">https://repo-fastly.voidlinux.org/</a> which
should be the generally fastest mirror for most users.  This mirror is
available now in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror</code> under the <em>World</em> region.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New utility for selecting XBPS mirrors</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/0-xmirror.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/0-xmirror</id>
		<published>2023-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>If you’ve ever had trouble <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/changing.html#manual-method">manually updating</a>
the mirror XBPS uses, fear no more!
You can now use the <a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xmirror.1"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror(1)</code></a> utility from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror</code>
package to select a mirror, either interactively (by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror</code> with root privileges) or
directly using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror --set</code>.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xmirror</code> will make switching to the new <a href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/01/fastly-fast-forward.html">Fastly-sponsored mirror</a>
extremely easy to do.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/xmirror.png" alt="screenshot of the main screen of xmirror in a terminal" /></p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Minor breaking change in service logging for several packages</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/log-service-change.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/02/log-service-change</id>
		<published>2023-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>As of <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/42026">this change</a> in void-packages,
all services provided by packages should start to include <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">log</code> sub-services that use
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/vlogger.8"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">vlogger(8)</code></a> as they are updated, if they did not already.
This means that service logs for all services should go to syslog now, where they can be captured
by a <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/config/services/logging.html">syslog daemon</a>.</p>

<p>However, there are a few services that manually log to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/var/log/$SERVICE_NAME</code>:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dnscrypt-proxy</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dqcache</code> (from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dq</code>)</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">preload</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">radicale</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">discosrv</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">relaysrv</code> (from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">syncthing</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>These services have been updated to use this new system, so they will no longer log to that directory.
If you wish to retain the previous behavior, you can set up <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/vlogger</code> like
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/vlogger.8#EXAMPLES">shown here</a>:</p>

<div class="language-sh highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">#!/bin/sh</span>
<span class="nb">exec </span>svlogd /var/log/<span class="nv">$1</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Void Accepted to Fastly Fast Forward!</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/01/fastly-fast-forward.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2023/01/fastly-fast-forward</id>
		<published>2023-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Did you know that Void has over 20 mirrors?  We have mirrors all over
the world, but just having a bunch of servers isn’t enough to
effectively deliver package updates to all Void users.  A mirror that
is nearby can have extremely good performance if you know it’s there
and switch to it, but for many people what we would like to offer is
just a URL that works anywhere in the world to provide the best
download experience available in that location.  When you look at what
we’re trying to achieve, its pretty clear we’d be trying to build a
content delivery network (CDN) for Void.</p>

<p>Rather than re-inventing the wheel, we reached out to the team at
Fastly to see if they’d be interested in working with us to improve
the default package experience for Void users globally.  We’re excited
to announce that the answer is yes; Void has been accepted to the
Fastly <a href="https://www.fastly.com/fast-forward">Fast Forward</a> program.
As part of this project, we’ll be provisioning a new repo URL that
will retrieve packages via Fastly’s global CDN.</p>

<p>Stay tuned over the next few weeks for the new mirror to become live,
and a post about how Void’s mirror infrastructure works!</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>US Mirror Issues</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/12/repo-us-issues.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/12/repo-us-issues</id>
		<published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The US mirror, <a href="https://repo-us.voidlinux.org/">repo-us.voidlinux.org</a>, is currently having hardware issues and is no longer syncing with the other mirrors for the time being.
Until this is fixed, <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/changing.html">switching to another mirror</a> is recommended.
There are <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">several other mirrors</a> located in the US that are still operational.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New Images! (October 2022 Edition)</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/10/new-images.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/10/new-images</id>
		<published>2022-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We’re pleased to announce that the 20221001 image set has been promoted to
current and is now generally available.</p>

<p>You can find the new images on our <a href="/download/">downloads page</a> and on our many
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">mirrors</a>.</p>

<p>Special thanks for this image set goes out to <a href="https://github.com/CameronNemo">@CameronNemo</a>
for work in fixing some of the issues with networking in the installer and
<a href="https://github.com/paper42">@paper42</a> for various improvements to the live
image contents.</p>

<p>Also in this release, the Raspberry Pi platform images are now condensed into
one image per architecture. See <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/installation/guides/arm-devices/platforms.html#supported-models">here</a>
for more details about which image to use for which Raspberry Pi model.</p>

<p>You may verify the authenticity of the images by following the instructions
on the downloads page, and using the following signify key information:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>untrusted comment: This key is only valid for images with date 20221001. public key
RWQ0DEc5FwYgp8wuGTRe3IWJGagpbeOpPqfSQbPIJie9GP8oBybejTqs
</code></pre></div></div>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Hacktoberfest 2022</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/09/hacktoberfest.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/09/hacktoberfest</id>
		<published>2022-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Are you ready for Hacktoberfest 2022?  Void Linux is!  We’re excited
to be participating for our 6th year.  Contributions that help to
address our out-of-date packages queue are especially welcome.  This
is a great way to dip your feet into the world of Linux distro package
management and what happens behind the scenes to provide a wide
selection of packages and make sure your system remains up to date.</p>

<p>Updating packages is very easy.  You can select a package from the
list of <a href="http://repo-default.voidlinux.org/void-updates/void-updates.txt">out of date
packages</a>
and update it using the tools in the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages">void-packages
repo</a>.  The
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md">manual</a>
might be of assistance when you are updating packages.</p>

<p>As a general rule, we recommend that newcomers to the Void Linux
project steer clear of “structural” packages unless you have specific
domain knowledge that qualifies you to work on high-risk packages.
When selecting a package to update, prefer packages registered to
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">orphan@voidlinux.org</code>.  These packages are otherwise unmaintained,
and your contribution will have a bigger impact.  You can update
packages that have a maintainer assigned, but understand that
conflicting changes between a maintainer and contributor will be
resolved at the discretion of Void staff.</p>

<p>Here are some useful tips when updating packages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>While we’re not completely opposed to PRs that add new packages,
you’re much more likely to get your PR approved and merged if it’s
a well written update.</li>
  <li>Don’t PR broken code. Our maintainers are much less likely to give
a second look to a PR that didn’t build when it was submitted.</li>
  <li>While it’s possible to run xbps-src from an alien distro, this
isn’t really supported.  If you’re a seasoned Linux user and want
to try Void, now is the time!</li>
  <li>The update list is sometimes wrong. We’d love to get patches that
improve its reliability by <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md#checking-for-new-upstream-releases">ignoring beta
versions</a>
or adding checks to packages that are not correctly detected as
out of date.</li>
  <li>If you have expertise in C, GNU Autotools, or other build systems,
taking a look at projects that we’ve marked as incompatible
with cross compilation and fixing the upstream issue can be
an amazing contribution that impacts more than just Void.</li>
</ul>

<p>Want to contribute but don’t know how to code?  No sweat!  We have a
documentation project that’s managed in git and can help you learn how
to use the tools of the trade without needing to simultaneously learn
how to manage our package build system.  Docs contributions should be
in the style of the manual, so make sure you <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/about/about-this-handbook.html">understand the
manual</a> and
feel free to open an issue or ask on IRC before starting on a larger
contribution to make sure your change can be accepted.</p>

<p>We look forward to working with the amazing world of open source
developers this month to improve Void and continue our high standards
for quality and reliability.  To ensure your PR has the best chance at
being accepted, feel free to reach out for help as explained in the
manual.  Together, we can make this a high-impact Hacktoberfest.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New Mirror Default</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/05/default-mirror.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2022/05/default-mirror</id>
		<published>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The default mirror has been updated to
https://repo-default.voidlinux.org.  If you wish to specify a mirror
that is nearer to you geographically you can find the full list of
currently active mirrors here:
<a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>US Mirror Retirement</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/10/mirror-retirement.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/10/mirror-retirement</id>
		<published>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The alpha.us.repo.voidlinux.org mirror has been retired.  Users should
switch to https://repo-us.voidlinux.org for continued service out of
the central US.  As part of the switch the US tier one mirror has
gained TLS, and is running on a more reliable host.</p>

<p>All contributors with in-flight PRs should rebase to ensure that the
latest URL is reflected in your branch’s CI configuration.</p>

</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Hacktoberfest 2021</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/hacktoberfest.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/hacktoberfest</id>
		<published>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Are you ready for Hacktoberfest 2021?  Void Linux is!  We’re excited
to be participating for our 5th year.  Contributions that help to
address our out-of-date packages queue are especially welcome.  This
is a great way to dip your feet into the world of Linux distro package
management and what happens behind the scenes to provide a wide
selection of packages and make sure your system remains up to date.</p>

<p>Updating packages is very easy.  You can select a package from the
list of <a href="http://repo-default.voidlinux.org/void-updates/void-updates.txt">out of date
packages</a>
and update it using the tools in the <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages">void-packages
repo</a>.  The
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md">manual</a>
might be of assistance when you are updating packages.</p>

<p>As a general rule, we recommend that newcommers to the Void Linux
project steer clear of “structural” packages unless you have specific
domain knowledge that qualifies you to work on high-risk packages.
When selecting a package to update, prefer packages registered to
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">orphan@voidlinux.org</code>.  These packages are otherwise unmaintained,
and your contribution will have a bigger impact.  You can update
packages that have a maintainer assigned, but understand that
conflicting changes between a maintainer and contributor will be
resolved at the discretion of Void staff.</p>

<p>Here are some useful tips when updating packages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>While we’re not completely opposed to PRs that add new packages,
you’re much more likely to get your PR approved and merged if it’s
a well written update.</li>
  <li>Don’t PR broken code. Our maintainers are much less likely to give
a second look to a PR that didn’t build when it was submitted.</li>
  <li>While it’s possible to run xbps-src from an alien distro, this
isn’t really supported.  If you’re a seasoned Linux user and want
to try Void, now is the time!</li>
  <li>The update list is sometimes wrong. We’d love to get patches that
improve its reliability by <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/blob/master/Manual.md#checking-for-new-upstream-releases">ignoring beta
versions</a>
or adding checks to packages that are not correctly detected as
out of date.</li>
  <li>If you have expertise in C, GNU Autotools, or other build systems,
taking a look at projects that we’ve marked as incompatible
with cross compilation and fixing the upstream issue can be
an amazing contribution that impacts more than just Void.</li>
</ul>

<p>We look forward to working with the amazing world of open source
developers this month to improve Void and continue our high standards
for quality and reliability.  To ensure your PR has the best chance at
being accepted, feel free to reach out for help as explained in the
manual.  Together, we can make this a high-impact Hacktoberfest.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>DigitalOcean Renews Sponsorship</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/sponsor-do-renew.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/09/sponsor-do-renew</id>
		<published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Void is pleased to announce that DigitalOcean has renewed their
sponsorship of our project as part of the <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/open-source/">Digital Ocean Open Source
program</a>.  DigitalOcean
provides us with reliable infrastructure on which we run the control
plane for our distributed fleet of machines, as well as some assorted
monitoring and fleet management services.  You can find our full list
of sponsors on the <a href="/acknowledgments/">Acknowledgements page</a>.</p>

<p>Should you also want to run a Void Linux VM on DigitalOcean’s droplet
service, we provide tooling for generating Void Linux images in <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-mklive">the
mklive repository</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Repository Signing Disruption</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/07/signing-disruption.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/07/signing-disruption</id>
		<published>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We are aware of an ongoing infrastructure issue affecting repository
synchronization and package signing.  We are working to resolve this
disruption, but first must resolve another unrelated infrastructure
issue.  We have no short term ETA for service restoration, however our
worst case resolution timeline is Friday the 23rd of July.</p>

<p>Your patience is appreciated while we perform this work as fast as
possible.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Void Linux freenode Channels Have Been Hijacked</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/freenode-takeover.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/freenode-takeover</id>
		<published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We have been made aware that during the mass channel takeover that is
ongoing on freenode that bogus <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">##voidlinux</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">##xbps</code> channels
have been created in the secondary namespace.</p>

<p>We do not operate or engage with these channels, and we do not
maintain an official presence on the freenode network.  We are still
in the process of finalizing the shutdown of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#xbps</code> and
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channels in the primary namespace, and have removed our
channels from the public listing as part of this process.</p>

<p>Though you should always exercise caution when running code obtained
from the internet, we urge you exercise extreme caution when using any
code from any channels on the freenode network that claims affiliation
with the Void Linux project.  You can always find our official points
of presence listed at the top of our <a href="/">home page</a>.</p>

<p>If you want to ask the Void team questions in real-time about this or
any other Void related matter, feel free to ask at any time in
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irc.libera.chat</code>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>IRC network switch to Libera</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/libera.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/05/libera</id>
		<published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>Given the recent <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/856543/">upheaval at Freenode</a>, the
Void Linux team has made the decision to switch to another IRC network. Our
network of choice is <a href="https://libera.chat">libera.chat</a>, managed by former
Freenode staff. When accessing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#xbps</code>, be sure to use
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irc.libera.chat</code>! We are excited to welcome you there, and hope this doesn’t
inconvenience anyone unduly. Be sure to let us know of any issues.</p>

<p>Contacting us will remain the same: you can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://libera.chat">libera.chat</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>In memoriam pullmoll</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/In-memoriam-pullmoll.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/In-memoriam-pullmoll</id>
		<published>2021-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><center>
	<img src="/assets/img/pullmoll.png" alt="Picture of Pullmoll" />
</center>

<p>Today, we were informed that our long time contributor and maintainer Jürgen
Buchmüller (pullmoll) has passed away.</p>

<p>With boundless dedication, Jürgen was one of the most prolific contributors to
the Void project and sponsored the project financially, too.</p>

<p>He invested lots of his time in keeping GCC up to date and well tested, supplied tons of
patches to port packages to new compilers and platforms and also took care of
(co-)maintaining many packages, including several non-trivial ones, like OpenJDK
and LibreOffice.</p>

<p>He was not only a dedicated and driven developer in the Void Linux project, he
also was one of the friendliest and warmest people we had the pleasure to work
with. Jürgen will be missed as a steady force and a calm and wise voice in
discussions. Most of all, he will be remembered as a friend to all of us.</p>

<p>Our thoughts and condolences go out to Jürgen’s family, friends, and loved ones.</p>

<p><strong>Thank you, pullmoll.</strong></p>

<p>– The Void Linux maintainers</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Friday in the Void: OpenSSL and Kernel Hardening</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/OpenSSL-hardening-updates.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/03/OpenSSL-hardening-updates</id>
		<published>2021-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The previously announced <a href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL.html">OpenSSL switch</a>
is now underway. Because OpenSSL is a dependency of a large number of packages,
the full rebuild process is expected to take several days. Syncing between the
builders and public repositories has been suspended to ensure that the package
tree remains consistent. Consequently, no new package updates will appear until
the switch is complete.</p>

<p>Once updates appear, we recommend that you perform a complete system update to
simplify the transition. Partial updates are possible, but you will need to
manually trace all OpenSSL dependants installed on your system and update them
atomically.</p>

<hr />

<p>Since 2016, the default bootloader configuration in Void Linux has set
the Linux kernel command-line options <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">slub_debug=P</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">page_poison=1</code> to
provide some level of kernel hardening. Kernel series 5.3 and later offer
alternative measures <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free</code> (see <a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux/commit/6471384af">this kernel
commit</a>).</p>

<p>Void’s kernels come with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> option enabled by default where
available (<em>i.e.</em>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.4&gt;=5.4.102</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.10&gt;=5.10.20</code> and
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linux5.11&gt;=5.11.3</code>). In most cases, you should not disable this option, as it
has a fairly minimal impact on performance (within 1%). The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free</code>
option is more expensive (around 5% on average) and needs to be enabled by hand
by passing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free=1</code> on the kernel command line. Similarly,
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc</code> can be disabled if needed by passing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_alloc=0</code>.</p>

<p>As a consequence of these changes, Void’s default kernel command-line now omits
the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">slub_debug</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">page_poison</code> options. There is a chance that your
existing system still has the old options enabled. They still work in newer
kernels, but have a performance impact more in line with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">init_on_free=1</code>. On
older hardware this can be quite noticeable. If you are running a kernel series
older than 5.4, you can keep them (or add them) for extra security at the cost
of performance; otherwise, you should remove them.</p>

<hr />

<p>As always, if you experience any issues, feel free to reach out to us! You can
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an issue</a> on
GitHub or seek help in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Switching back to OpenSSL</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/OpenSSL</id>
		<published>2021-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>The Void Linux team is <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/21056">switching back to
OpenSSL</a> on March 5th,
2021 (2021-03-05).</p>

<p>For most users, there should be no noticeable change. If you have any packages
installed that are no longer provided by Void, or your system has explicit
dependencies on LibreSSL, you will of course need to take action to ensure your
system continues to function after the switch.</p>

<p>If you experience any issues, feel free to reach out to us! You can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>A discussion about switching to OpenSSL began in a Request For Comments (RFC)
posted on April 12th, 2020, at
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/20935">void-linux/void-packages#20935</a>.
Since then, a majority of Void maintainers have expressed support for the move.
The main reasons for the switch are as listed in the RFC:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Because most software targets OpenSSL, Void will no longer have to maintain
(in some cases, very complex) patches to support LibreSSL. The complexity of
the OpenSSL API makes such patching burdensome and risky, with mistakes
potentially causing runtime errors or security issues - we have avoided
those, as far as we know, but this has required a lot of effort.</li>
  <li>Extensive support for platform specific optimizations outside of x86.</li>
  <li>Access to new standards and algorithms earlier, such as full TLS 1.3 support.</li>
</ul>

<p>As a result of the above, the switch to OpenSSL is expected to lessen the time
and effort spent on packages that require an OpenSSL-like library. This is
especially notable because most other distributions which used LibreSSL have
dropped it, so there aren’t as many people amongst whom to distribute the
effort.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Alpine, which switched to LibreSSL temporarily, switched back to OpenSSL in
January 2019, with the <a href="https://alpinelinux.org/posts/Alpine-3.9.0-released.html">3.9.0
release</a>.</li>
  <li>More recently, Gentoo, which used to offer LibreSSL as an option, has
<a href="https://www.gentoo.org/support/news-items/2021-01-05-libressl-support-discontinued.html">discontinued that
support</a>
as well.</li>
</ul>

<p>For further context, LWN <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/841664/">covered the subject of LibreSSL on
Linux</a> at the beginning of this year. The
article also covers the attention and improvements that the OpenSSL project has
received post-Heartbleed, which was one of the main reasons for Void’s initial
switch to LibreSSL.</p>

<p>For an example of extra work caused by packages that expect OpenSSL, Void’s
version of Qt5 is heavily patched in order to properly support LibreSSL.
Furthermore, the just released Qt6 would also need significant effort to be
patched and maintained to use LibreSSL, without the possibility of such effort
being upstreamed.</p>

<p>At the same time, other software can have limited functionality or hit edge
cases when using LibreSSL, due to not being thoroughly tested with it. One
example is Python, which is limited in the ciphers available to running
programs, since it depends on what the SSL library provides - they are even
<a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0644/#libressl-support">considering dropping any support for LibreSSL in the
future</a>. Another
example is OpenVPN, which we have received bug reports for connection issues
with LibreSSL
(<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/23413">void-linux/void-packages#23413</a>).
This required us to switch the package to use Mbed TLS by default, resulting in
some limitations to the resulting package. With the switch to OpenSSL, the
OpenVPN package will now be provided in the most widely deployed and tested
configuration, so similar compatibility hiccups are unlikely to reappear.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this move has required us to drop some packages that rely on the
OpenSSL 1.0.1 API; while LibreSSL maintains compatibility with this legacy API,
modern OpenSSL has abandoned it.</p>

<p>One great feature of LibreSSL not offered by OpenSSL is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libtls</code> library,
which aims to be a hard to misuse interface for communicating over the web
safely, with sane defaults. Some of the packages we ship depend on it, so work
has been done to package a standalone version of it in
<a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/pull/28732">void-linux/void-packages#28732</a>.</p>

<p>The Void Linux team is grateful for the work of the OpenBSD community on
<a href="https://github.com/libressl-portable/portable">libressl-portable</a>, we have
greatly benefited from their work. Void continues to package other excellent
OpenBSD software, including OpenSSH and signify, which is our tool of choice
for signing live images.</p>

<p>In conclusion, we expect our switch to OpenSSL to ease maintenance overhead,
provide the same reliable experience to users, and improve functionality in
select packages. Look forward to the update landing some time after March 5th!</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>New Images!</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/new-images.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/02/new-images</id>
		<published>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p>We’re pleased to announce that the 20210218 image set has been
promoted to current and is now generally available.</p>

<p>You can find the new images on our <a href="/download/">downloads page</a> and on
our many <a href="https://docs.voidlinux.org/xbps/repositories/mirrors/index.html">mirrors</a>.</p>

<p>Special thanks for this image set goes out to @ericonr for work in
validating the images, and to @paper42 for providing us a new image in
the grub splash screen.</p>

<p>You may verify the authenticity of the images by following the
instructions on the downloads page, and using the following signify
key information:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>untrusted comment: This key is only valid for images with date 20210218. public key
RWRSNnH5WbLx1EWUgJGeccx/Dof1MH5k5tZFytMlIOgpRJvRxHJtMqrP
</code></pre></div></div>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title>Upcoming glibc upgrade requires updates for other packages on 32-bit machines</title>
		<link href="https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/01/glibc-2.32.html"/>
		<id>https://voidlinux.org/news/2021/01/glibc-2.32</id>
		<published>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="xhtml">
			<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
				<p><p><strong>Note:</strong> This only applies to users of Void’s glibc version on 32-bit
machines. If the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps-uhelper arch</code> prints something other than
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i686</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv7l</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv6l</code>, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">armv6l-musl</code>, you don’t need to do
anything.</p>

<p>Void Linux currently packages glibc version 2.30, but is going to update to
2.32 soon, together with the long awaited GCC 10. Since this new version makes
use of new system calls, due to the ongoing time64 (support for times after
2038 on 32-bit platforms) work on glibc, applications with restrictive seccomp
filters that haven’t been rebuilt for the new glibc version <strong>will stop
working</strong>. Packages with such issues include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">firefox</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chromium</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qt5-webengine</code> (and consequently dependants, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">qutebrowser</code>)</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">electron*</code> (and consequently dependants, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">element-desktop</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>We will be pushing updates to these packages <em>before</em> the glibc update, if
possible, but it won’t be possible for all of them. This includes <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code>,
which means you can be <strong>locked out of your system</strong> if that’s what you use to
access it and you perform a partial upgrade that only includes the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code>
package.</p>

<p>Therefore, even though Void enables partial upgrades, you should perform a full
system upgrade when <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code> appears in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xbps-install -Su</code> list. Be sure to
test these packages - for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssh</code> this includes actually opening a session,
since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sshd</code> itself runs without issue. If for some reason something in your
system stops working, you can of course reinstall the old <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">glibc</code> package using
<a href="https://man.voidlinux.org/xtools.1">xdowngrade(1)</a> from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">xtools</code> package:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code># xdowngrade /var/cache/xbps/glibc-2.30_2.x86_64.xbps /var/cache/xbps/glibc-locales-2.30_2.x86_64.xbps
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If we missed some package with this issue, please let us know! You can <a href="https://github.com/void-linux/void-packages/issues/new">open an
issue</a> on GitHub or
ping us in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#voidlinux</code> channel on <a href="https://freenode.net">https://freenode.net</a>.</p>
</p>
			</div>
		</content>
	</entry>


</feed>
